Raphael Soyer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Raphael Soyer papers
1933-1989
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Soyer, Raphael
3.9 linear feet
The papers of realist painter Raphael Soyer date from 1933 to 1989 and measure 3.9 linear feet. They document Soyer's career as a painter, printmaker, and writer. Found within the papers are scattered biographical materials, including several transcripts of interviews with Soyer; extensive personal and professional correspondence; writings and notes by Soyer and others; scattered legal and financial records; exhibition materials, clippings and other printed material; and photographs of Soyer in his studio, with artists and friends, and at art events. Also found are one sketch and a facsimile of Soyer's 1968 sketchbook produced by Forum Gallery.
Provenance
Portions of the collection were donated by Raphael Soyer between 1961 and 1980. Additional materials were donated in 1991 and 1993 by his widow, Rebecca, and his grandson, Joseph Leiber, on behalf of the entire Soyer family.
Separated Material
Originals of loaned material, including a small amount of correspondence and three sketchbooks, were returned to Raphael Soyer after microfilming in 1968. Loaned material is available on reel N68-1 but is not described in the container listing in this finding aid.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art are several collections related to Raphael Soyer: Esther Reier letter from Raphael Soyer, 1978 May 29; Raphael Soyer's Artist Statement from 1947; a Raphael Soyer lecture from 1960; the papers of his twin brother, Moses Soyer; Brooklyn Museum interviews of artists, circa 1965-1968 (includes an interview of Soyer); and the Karl E. Fortess taped interviews with artists, 1963-1985, which also includes an interview with Raphael Soyer. The Archives of American Art's Oral History collection has an interview of Raphael Soyer dated May 13-June 1, 1981 conducted by Milton Brown.
Additional Raphael Soyer papers, 1949-1954, are available at Cornell University.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of this collection was digitized in 2009 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website. Materials which have not been scanned include photographs of works of art, select draft writings by Soyer, writings by others on unrelated topics, and certain routine financial documents and printed material. Exhibition catalogs have had their covers and relevant pages scanned.
Restrictions on Access
Use of the original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Raphael Soyer (1899-1987) and his twin brother Moses (1899-1974) were born on December 25, 1899, in the Russian town Borisoglebsk. Their father Abraham was a scholar and Hebrew teacher who encouraged all of his children to sketch and paint. After the family was deported from Russia, they settled in the Bronx, New York, in 1912. Raphael and Moses briefly attended school, but at 16 they began working various jobs to help support their family. They also began taking free art classes at Cooper Union and later Raphael attended the National Academy of Design and the Art Students League where he studied with Guy Pene du Bois. He began to show his paintings in 1926 and in 1929 gallery owner Charles Daniel gave him his first one man show. Soyer became one of the leading realist painters and printmakers, often depicting Depression-era transients, Manhattan streetscapes, shoppers, and women at work. He also painted and sketched numerous self-portraits and portraits of fellow artists and cultural figures, many of whom were also his friends, including Allen Ginsberg, Chaim Gross, Edward Hopper, and Arshile Gorky.
Beginning in the 1930s Soyer showed his work frequently at the Whitney Museum of American Art, Associated American Artists Galleries, National Collection of Fine Arts, and other national and international exhibitions. During the 1940s and 1950s he was a leading advocate of realism and spoke out against the abstract style that was dominating the New York art scene. In 1953 he co-founded Reality magazine.
Soyer joined the Forum Gallery in New York in the early 1960s and became good friends with his dealer Bella Fishko. Also during the 1960s he published three books, A Painter's Pilgrimage (1962), Homage to Thomas Eakins (1966), and Self-Revealment: a Memoir (1969), and had his first retrospective at the Whitney Museum in 1967.
Throughout his career Soyer also occasionally taught at art schools including the Art Students League and the New School. He also collaborated with his friend, writer Isaac Bashevis Singer, by illustrating several of Singer's books. Soyer and his wife Rebecca, whom he married in 1931, lived the rest of their lives in New York City, but often traveled to Europe. They had one daughter, Mary. Soyer's final book, Diary of an Artist, was published in 1977 and in 1979 he received the Gold Medal from the National Arts Club. He continued painting realist subjects until his death in 1987.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of realist painter Raphael Soyer date from 1933 to 1989 and measure 3.9 linear feet. They document Soyer's career as a painter, printmaker, and writer. Found within the papers are scattered biographical materials, including several transcripts of interviews with Soyer; extensive personal and professional correspondence; writings and notes by Soyer and others; scattered legal and financial records; exhibition materials, clippings and other printed material; and photographs of Soyer in his studio, with artists and friends, and at art events. Also found are one sketch and a facsimile of Soyer's 1968 sketchbook produced by Forum Gallery.
Biographical materials include award certificates, including a 1975 certificate from the National Academy of Design, lists of artwork by Soyer, and several transcripts of interviews with Raphael Soyer in which he discusses topics such as his career as an artist, artists in New York City, and the inspiration for his artwork.
Personal and professional correspondence is with numerous artists, writers, art historians, curators, gallery owners, arts organizations, museums, and universities. Correspondents include Lambro Ahlas, Rudolf Baranik, George Biddle, John Bratby, David Burliuk, Peter De Francia, Lloyd Goodrich, Joseph Hirsch, Joseph Hirshhorn, Edward Hopper, Joe Lasker, Henry Varnum Poor, Isaac Bashevis Singer, and many others. Additional correspondence is addressed to Reality magazine, for which Soyer was an editor.
Writings and notes by Soyer include several drafts and notes for his four published books A Painter's Pilgrimage (1962), Homage to Thomas Eakins (1966), Self-Revealment: a Memoir (1969), and Diary of an Artist (1977). Also by Soyer are draft essays, lectures, and articles - many about social realism. Writings by others include essays and articles by artists and art scholars sent to Soyer for review.
Scattered legal and financial records include bank statements, receipts, leases, and documents related to the publishing of his books. Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs and announcements, clippings, and other published items.
Photographs depict Soyer in his studio, with other artists and friends such as Chaim Gross, Edward Hopper, and Jose De Creeft, and at art events, and include a few photographs of his artwork. Also found are one pencil sketch and a facsimile of Soyer's 1968 sketchbook produced by Forum Gallery.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1939-1986 (Box 1, OV 6; 12 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1940-1988 (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 3: Writings & Notes, circa 1946-1987 (Box 2-3; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Legal & Financial Records, 1959-1988 (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1933-1989 (Box 3-4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1953-1987 (Box 5, OV 6; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, 1968, undated (Box 5; 2 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Social realism--New York (State)--New York; Painting, American; Realism in art; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Printmakers--New York (State)--New York; Authors--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Interviews; Photographs; Writings; Sketchbooks
Names:
Ahlas, Lambro; Biddle, George, 1885-; Bratby, John, 1928-; Baranik, Rudolf; Burliuk, David, 1882-1967; De Francia, Peter; Goodrich, Lloyd, 1897-; Hirsch, Joseph, 1910-; Hirshhorn, Joseph H.; Hopper, Edward, 1882-1967; Poor, Henry Varnum, 1887-1970; Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1904-; Lasker, Joe
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1939-1986, Series 1:; (Box 1, OV 6; 12 folders)
  Scattered biographical documents about Raphael Soyer consist primarily of award certificates, including a 1975 certificate from the National Academy of Design, three lists of artwork by Soyer, and several transcripts of interviews with Raphael Soyer in which he discusses topics such as his career as an artist, artists in New York City, and the inspiration for his artwork. Interview transcripts are arranged alphabetically by interviewer.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Award Certificates, 1939, 1957, 1970s-1980s, (See also OV 6 for oversized certificates) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lists of Works of Art, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Medical Documents, 1986, (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership Cards, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rebecca Soyer Club Application, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Soyer Letterhead, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview Transcripts (Box 1)
    - Soyer Interviewed by Lawrence E. Abt and Stanley Rosner, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Soyer Interviewed by Rachel Chodorov, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Soyer Interviewed by Barbaralee Diamondstein, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Soyer Interviewed by Karl Fortess, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Soyer Interviewed by "F" (possibly Karl Fortess), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Soyer Interviewed by "G. R.," circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oversize Award Certificate, circa 1980s, (Scanned with Box 1, F1) (Box OV 6)
- Correspondence, 1940-1988, Series 2:; (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
  Raphael Soyer's correspondence spans over forty years, with the bulk of it dating between 1960 and his death in 1987. Letters are arranged chronologically and the majority are incoming to Soyer, but there are also scattered drafts of outgoing letters. Soyer was friends with many artists and cultural figures, and his personal correspondence includes letters to and from artists such as Lambro Ahlas, Benny Andrews, Rudolf Baranik, Leonard Baskin, George Biddle, Peter Blume, Aaron Bohrod, John Bratby, Alex Brook, David Burliuk, Marc Chagall, Peter De Francia, Otto Dix, Guy Du Bois, Philip Evergood, Josef Herman, Joseph Hirsch, Edward Hopper, Jacob Kainen, R. B. Kitaj, Leon Kroll, Joe Lasker, Jack Levine, Jacques Lipchitz, Henry Varnum Poor, Fairfield Porter, Max Weber, and numerous others. Soyer also corresponded with many writers such as Erskine Caldwell, Allen Ginsberg, Marianne Moore, and Isaac Bashevis Singer.
  Also found here is correspondence with the Forum Gallery which represented him and dealer Bella Fishko. There is also correspondence with numerous galleries, museums, and schools which exhibited his work or requested his work for potential exhibitions. Additionally, there is correspondence with students and publishers, mostly requests for him to lecture or write articles, and business correspondence on the sale, donation, or commission of his work. Soyer corresponded with many art historians and critics, curators, gallery owners, and collectors, such as Andrei Chegodaev, Lloyd Goodrich, Joseph Hirshhorn, Abram Lerner, and Carl Zigrosser, as well as arts and social organizations. The collection includes very little family correspondence. Some of the letters are in Russian.
  See index for List of Correspondents from Series 2.
  List of Correspondents for Series 2
  A. S. Barnes & Company, Inc.: 1965, 1976
  Abeles, Sigmund: 1981, 1987
  Abram, Carl Fisher: 1986
  ACA Galleries: 1981, 1985
  Ackerberg, Sanders: 1974
  Ahlas, Lambro: 1964, 1965, 1971, 1973, 1975, 1976, 1978-1980, 1985, 1986, undated
  Alderson, Cella: undated
  Alexander, Sidney: 1962, 1978, undated
  Algase, Benjamin: 1981
  Allen, Mary: 1980
  Allentuck, Dan: 1986
  Allinson, Jane: 1985
  American Academy and Institute of Arts and letters: 1981, 1987
  American Art Journal: 1970
  American Contemporary Art Gallery: 1968
  Amsden, Floyd T.: 1978
  Andrews, Benny: 1965, 1972, 1974
  Arikha, Avigdor: 1985-1987, undated
  Art Dealers Association of America, Inc.: 1984
  Art Harris Gallery: 1972, 1974
  Art News: 1953, 1963
  Art Students League of New York: 1968
  Artists for Core: 1966
  Ashkenazy, Arnold: 1984, 1986
  Associated American Artists: 1961, 1965, 1968
  Atelier Royce: 1977
  Bakshi, Ralph: 1978
  Baranik, Rudolf: 1961, 1962, 1964, 1973, 1974, undated
  Baskin, Leonard: 1963, 1964, undated
  Bearden, Romare: undated
  Bender, William H., Jr.: 1967
  Berman, Saul: 1970, undated
  Bernstein, Bo: 1973
  Bezalel National Museum: 1963
  Biddle, George: 1957, 1962, 1966, 1967, 1971
  Biegle, Peter: undated
  Bloch, Maurice: 1981
  Bloch, Robert: 1984, 1985, undated
  Blume, Peter: 1967, 1969
  Bohrod, Aaron: 1954, 1960, 1977, 1979
  Boston Public Library: 1963
  Boston University: 1961, 1965
  Bouche, Louis: 1960
  Bowdoin College Museum of Art: 1964, 1968
  Boyle, Kay: 1983
  Bratby, John: 1962, 1965-1968, 1970, 1973, 1974, 1981, 1982, 1984, 1986, 1987, undated
  Braun, Walter: 1977
  Brook, Alex: 1969, 1977
  Brooklyn Association for Mental Health, Inc.: 1969
  Brooklyn Community Counseling Center: 1964
  Brooklyn Museum: 1966, 1986
  Brooks, Van Wyck: 1962, undated
  Brown, Margaret Root: 1962
  Browne, Renni: undated
  Bulla, Clyde Robert: 1978
  Burliuk, David Marussia: 1959-1961, 1963, 1966
  Burliuk, Nicholas: 1967, 1982, 1983, undated
  Burston Graphic Centre, Jerusalem: 1975
  Butler Institute of American Art: 1963, 1984, 1987
  Butler, Joseph G.: 1963
  Caldwell, Virginia: 1978, 1979, 1982, 1983, 1985, 1986, undated
  Carvalho, Milton A.: 1968, 1969
  Castellon, Hieda: 1977
  Centre Culturel Americain: 1979
  Chagall, Marc: 1955, 1957
  Chapnick, Paul: 1980
  Charnow, Miriam: 1964
  Chegodaev, A.: 1965, 1966, 1969, 1973, 1974, 1976, 1977, 1979, undated
  Chernow, Burt: 1966
  Chicago Tribune: 1953
  Chute, Marchette: 1961, 1966, 1969, 1981
  Ciardi, John: 1966, 1969
  Cogen, Charlie: 1975
  Cohen, Arthur: 1975-1977, 1979, 1980
  Coleman, Edward: 1975
  Connellan, Carl: 1972
  Constructionist: 1966
  Copper, Dennis: 1976
  Corbin, Douglas: 1981
  Corcoran Gallery of Art: 1943, 1951
  Cornell University: 1962, 1965
  Dale, Marion: 1972
  De Francia, Peter: 1961, 1968, 1976, 1981, 1984, 1986
  De Groot, P.: 1965
  Delbanco, Kurt: 1981
  Deldeo, Salvatore: 1979
  Detroit Institute of Arts: 1963
  Diamond, David: 1977
  Dickinson, Edwin: undated
  Dickinson, Sidney: 1959
  Dix, Otto: 1963
  Dmitrievitch, Andrei: 1976, undated
  Dobkin, John: 1983, undated
  Du Bois, Guy: 1951, 1953, 1955
  Eaton, Charles Edwar: 1978, 1979
  Edel, Leon: 1969
  Edgeworth, Richard C.: 1984, 1986
  Evergood, Philip: 1941, 1954, 1967, undated
  Everson Museum of Art: 1976, 1977
  Feinberg, Charles E.: 1947
  Feinberg, Paul: 1986
  Fiala, Vaclav: 1975, 1978
  Fisher, Jacob: 1979
  Flaig, Bea: 1981
  Floch, Joseph: 1962, undated
  Fogg Art Museum: 1974, 1975
  Ford Foundation: 1962
  Forum Gallery (Bella Fishko): 1961-1963, 1966-1968, 1970, 1973-1975, 1977, 1980, 1982, 1985, 1986, undated
  Frankenstein, Alfred V.: 1971
  Franklin, Elaine: 1974
  Freifeld, Eric: 1968, 1972, 1978
  Friends of Art: 1985
  Fuks, Leo: 1975
  Furth, Dora: 1973, 1975-1977
  Garrett, Adams: 1982, 1986
  George Mason University: 1980
  Georgia Museum of Art: 1968, 1983
  Gibbs, Charles: 1972
  Gillette, Henry: 1981
  Ginsberg, Allen: 1968
  Gladstein, Sheldon: 1987
  Glaser, Mary Todd: 1965
  Goldsmith, Morton G.: 1964
  Gonzales, Xavier: 1982
  Goodrich, Lloyd: 1963, 1967, 1971, 1981, undated
  Goshans, Werner: 1977, 1981, 1982
  Grant, Quentin: 1979
  Grausman, Philip: 1965, undated
  Gray, Don: 1984
  Grossman, Emery: 1964
  Grosz, George: 1956, 1957
  Guggenheim Museum: 1980
  Guttuso, Renato: 1962, 1963, undated
  Gwathney, Bob: undated
  Halegua, Lillian: 1967, 1977
  Halper, Albert: 1972
  Harmon, Lily: 1981
  Harris, Victor: 1977
  Harriton, Abe: 1981
  Harry N. Abrams, Inc.: 1964, 1969, 1971
  Harvard University: 1962
  Hautzig, Debbi: 1978
  Hebrew Union College: 1983
  Hecht, Fels: 1984, 1987
  Heckscher Museum: 1977, 1987
  Herman, Josef: 1967, 1976, 1983, undated
  Hills, Patricia: 1981, 1982, 1985
  Hirsch, Joseph: 1960, 1964, 1966, 1977, 1979, 1981
  Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden: 1975, 1979-1983
  Hirshhorn, Joseph: 1965, 1968, 1969
  Hoag, Paul Sterling: 1954
  Hoffman, Gladys: 1961
  Hollfelder, Jack: 1983
  Homar, Lorenzo: 1979, 1980
  Hopper, Edward: 1960-1963, undated
  Horn, Lex: 1964
  Horowitz, Brenda: 1984
  Hosbach, Marguerette: 1973
  Hutchins, Robert: 1984, undated
  Jackson, Harry: 1966
  Jackson, Valentina: 1979
  Jewish Museum: 1974, 1981, 1982
  Johns, Judith: 1982
  Jones, Kathryn: 1986
  Jones, Wilma: 1960
  Josephson, Matthew: 1969, 1970
  Kainen, Jacob: 1968, 1969
  Kalet, Maureen: 1982
  Kalischer, Nathan: 1979
  Kane, Doris: 1975
  Kaplan, Kathy Walden: 1983
  Karlstrom, Paul: 1972
  Kearney, John: 1984, undated
  Kennedy Galleries, Inc.: 1980
  King, Barry: 1985
  King, Raymond: 1986
  Kitaj, R. B and Sandra: 1979-1985, 1987, undated
  Klemeri, Diana: 1982
  Knaths, Karl: 1953
  Kroll, Leon: 1945, 1961, 1964
  Kuniyoshi, Yasuo: undated
  Kunstverein in Hamburg: 1980
  Landau, Ellen G.: 1982
  Lasansky, Leonardo: 1986
  Lasker, Joe: 1955, 1962, 1968, 1970, 1985, undated
  Leiser, Erwin: 1980
  Lerner, Abram (Al): 1958, 1985
  LeRoy, Marvyn: 1968
  Lesser, Gerson: 1979
  Levin, Eli: 1977
  Levin, Gail: 1985
  Levine, David: 1963, 1971
  Levine, Jack: 1963, 1986
  Levine, Sheldon: 1987
  Levy, Alan; 1982, 1983, 1985
  Lipchitz, Jacques: 1962, undated
  Loeb, Albert: 1980
  Long, Rose: 1986
  Loyola Marymount University: 1985, 1986
  Ludgin, Earle: 1966
  Lyons, Leonard: 1963
  Maass, John: 1986
  Maryland Institute, College of Art: 1975
  Mayer, Bena Frank: 1967
  Mayer, Bernadette: 1981
  Mazo, Joe: 1984
  McBain, Gertrude: 1986, undated
  McDaniel, Aletha: 1982
  Metropolitan Museum of Art: 1978-1980, 1982-1984, 1986
  Meyers, Bill: 1962, undated
  Miami Herald: 1972
  Milwaukee Art Museum: 1983
  Minnigerode, C. Powell: 1940
  Mishkan Le'Omanut, Museum of Art: 1964
  Mondale, Joan: 1977
  Moore, Marianne: 1960, 1968
  Morgan, Bill: 1984
  Morlan, Nina: 1983
  Mourlot, Liliane: 1967
  Mumford, Lewis: 1965
  Museum of Modern Art: 1953, 1961, 1962, 1966
  Museum Tel Aviv: 1962, 1972, 1973
  Myers, Neil: 1973
  Nathan, Helmuth: 1967
  National Academy of Design: 1970, 1977, 1981, 1984
  National Arts Club: 1978
  National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc.: 1968
  Neel, Alice & Neel Family: 1969, 1985
  Neugass, Ludwig: 1965
  New Republic Book Company, Inc.: 1976, 1977
  New School for Social Research: 1980
  New York Times: 1959, 1972, undated
  Newark Public Library: 1981
  Newman, John: 1984
  Nichols, Norma: 1982
  Nordness, Leo: 1961
  Otis, Elizabeth R.: 1963
  Palevsky, Jaon: 1980
  Papazian, Gilbert: 1977, 1978, 1980, 1987
  Parrish Art Museum: 1980
  Pembroke Gallery: 1983
  Penney, Charles: 1981
  Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts: 1948
  Pennsylvania State University: 1977, 1982, 1983
  Perlis, Don: 1979
  Perlman, Bennard: 1977
  Petrovsky, Mira & Vladimir: 1975, undated
  Pink, Marilyn: 1986
  Poor, Henry Varnum & Annie: 1957, 1960, 1962, 1966, 1969, 1975, 1985, undated
  Porter, Fairfield: 1956, undated
  Portland Art Museum: 1985
  Provincetown Art Association: 1984
  Queens Child Guidance Center, Inc.: 1970
  Quirt, Eleanor: 1981, 1985, undated
  Randolph-Macon Woman's College: 1985
  Random House, Inc.: 1968, 1969, 1976
  Rappin, Adrian: 1976
  Rewald, John & Alice: 1963, 1966, 1982, undated
  Rhode Island School of Design: 1971
  Robbins, Warren: 1983, 1984, 1985
  Rogers, Leo M.: 1961
  Rose, Herman: 1962, undated
  Rosenberg, James N.: 1969
  Rosenkranz, Rita: 1987
  Rosner, Stanley: 1969
  Roszak, Theodore: 1977
  Roth, Audrey M.: 1978
  Rothwell, Jed: 1987
  Rozmaryn, Jack: 1974
  Russell, Rhoda Winter: 1980
  Saint John's University: 1981
  Salisbury, Harrison: 1975
  Salpeter, Harry: 1964, undated
  San Antonio Museum Association: 1980
  San Francisco Museum of Modern Art: 1982
  Sandler, Marc J.: 1962
  Sarnewitz, Lyle Evan: 1984
  Schiff, Sidney: 1984
  Schlang, Joseph: 1965
  Schoen, Jason: 1985, 1986
  Schrag, Karl: 1969, undated
  Schrag, Raymond: 1986
  Seyffert, Richard: 1979
  Shannon, Joe: 1981
  Shapiro, David: 1979
  Shubert, Katherine: 1967
  Singer, Isaac B.: 1978, undated
  Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture: 1981
  Sleigh, Sylvia: 1984
  Smith, Mrs. Wallace (Kelcey): 1985
  Smith, Vincent D.: 1976, 1981
  Smithsonian Institution (National Collection of Fine Arts): 1968, 1973, 1977, 1979, 1981, 1982, 1985-1987
  Sonnemann, Nell: 1972, 1977, 1979, 1981, 1985, 1986
  Styron, William: 1969
  Swanson, Mary T.: 1979
  Syracuse University: 1965, 1973
  Taliano, A. D.: 1978, 1981, undated
  Tapper, Joan: 1977
  Thaler, Jesse: 1978
  Tinsley, Betty: 1961
  Todd, Ellen: 1986
  Todorchev, Anne: 1979, 1980
  Tolskaya, Leidmila: 1965, 1967
  Toney, Anthony: 1955
  United American Artists: 1940
  United Jewish Appeal of Greater New York: 1970, 1974
  University of California, Berkeley: 1966
  University of Maryland: 1968
  University of Minnesota: 1985, 1986
  University of Texas: 1969
  Van der Tweel, L. H.: 1975
  Van Devanter, Ann C.: 1973
  Vereisky, Oriest: undated
  Vincent Price Collection: 1964
  Walsh, Alexandria: 1977
  Warner, Keith: 1944
  Warshaw, Howard: 1953
  Washburn, Gordon B.: 1967
  Weber, Max: 1954, undated
  Wertham, Fredric: 1967
  West, Michael: 1967
  Wheelock, Susan; 1976
  Whitney Museum of American Art: 1950, 1966, 1969, 1977, 1979, 1981-1983, 1985
  Wichita Art Museum: 1977
  Wigglesworth, Anne Parker: 1983
  William A. Farnsworth Library and Art Museum, 1981, 1985-1987, undated
  Winer, Arthur: 1976
  Wolff, Theodore: 1981
  Worcester Art Museum (Francis Henry Taylor): 1957
  Yeshiva University: 1967, 1974
  Zabriskie, Virginia: 1979
  Zigrosser, Carl: 1941, 1969
  - Correspondence, 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1959, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1969, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-24)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979, (16 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25-40)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1988, (16 folders) (Box 1, Folder 41-56)
  - Undated Correspondence, A-Z, circa 1940-1987, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1940-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters Addressed to Reality, 1953-1954, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Letters Addressed to Reality, Undated Letters, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Writings & Notes, circa 1946-1987, Series 3:; (Box 2-3; 1.5 linear feet)
  The Writings & Notes series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Writings & Notes by Soyer, circa 1946-1987
  Subseries 3.2: Writings & Notes by Others, 1953-1984
  - Writings & Notes by Soyer, circa 1946-1987, Subseries 3.1: